Finding Aid for Borman Family Papers, 1923-1991
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Borman Family Papers 1923-1991 1960-1987
Borman family.
0468 Aa 2; Ac
The Borman Family is a prominent Detroit area Jewish-American family and is best known for opening a string of supermarket chains throughout southeastern Michigan. Farmer Jack Market was the most successful venture, but others before it included Food Fair and Savon. Founded by two Russian-born brothers, Borman's Inc. remained a family-run business until 1987 when Farmer Jack was sold to the Great Atlantic & Pacific Tea Company (A&P). This collection primarily represents the family business, but also covers the Borman Family's extensive involvement in the Detroit and Jewish-American communities.
7 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This material was donated by Gilbert Borman (donor no. 9401 ) in November 2003.
The collection is open to research.
Tom and Abraham (Al) Borman were brothers who emigrated from Russia in 1914, eventually settling in the Detroit area. Together, they opened their first store, Tom's Quality Market, in 1927. By 1935 they had ten markets, and by 1955 they had 26, which operated under the names of "Food Fair" and "Lucky." The Borman brothers soon decided to merge the stores and incorporate them under the name of "Food Fair" Markets. Between 1956 and 1964 they continued to open new stores as well as acquire smaller local chains, resulting in their doubling in size to 52 stores total.
Borman's Inc. quickly became well known in the supermarket business for its stores' low prices and quick growth, and on January 20, 1959, the company made its first public offering of stock, trading on the New York Stock Exchange. Besides Food Fair Markets, Borman's Inc. also opened a chain of 7 discount food stores under the name "Savon," and was the first company to enter into an agreement with K-mart to operate a supermarket within the discount chain. Borman's Inc. expanded and diversified further by buying up other companies such as Detroit Pure Milk Company (1962), the Wesley Quaker Maid Ice Cream Company (1963), and several department stores and drugstores.
Probably the best known of the Borman's Inc. endeavors was Farmer Jack, which the company opened in 1965. The strategy behind the supermarket was to offer a large variety of quality products at the lowest possible prices, and it proved so successful that all Food Fair, K-mart, and Savon stores were consolidated under the same name of "Farmer Jack."
Although Tom Borman retired from the company in 1967, Borman's Inc. remained a family-run business throughout its existence. Abraham Borman continued to be involved with the company, and his son, Paul Borman, groomed for the family business for years, took over as president of Borman's Inc. in 1965. Paul would continue to head the company until it was ultimately merged with A & P in 1988.
Beyond creating and managing a successful supermarket business, the Bormans, especially Abraham and his son, Paul, were highly active in the Detroit area, attending events with such high profile politicians as Governors William Milliken and George Romney, and Detroit Mayor Coleman Young. Paul Borman served as the director of several boards including the United Foundation, the Detroit Symphony, the Detroit Economic Growth Corporation, First Federal Savings and Loan Association of Michigan, and the University of Detroit. The Bormans were also very involved in the Jewish-American community, and received awards and accolades from the Israeli government as well as prominent Jewish-American societies.
The papers of the Borman Family relate primarily to their Detroit area supermarket chains and includes organizational papers related to Borman's Inc. and Farmer Jack. Substantial visual materials are to be found throughout the collection documenting all aspects of the business, but especially public relations activities. This collection also contains materials related to the Borman Family history and the Bormans' lives outside of the supermarket business.
Subjects:
Borman family.; Borman's Inc.; Charities--Michigan--Detroit Metropolitan Area.; Detroit (Mich.)--Commerce.; Farmer Jack (Grocery stores); Grocery stores--Michigan--Detroit Metropolitan Area.; Jews--Michigan--Detroit Metropolitan Area.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Borman family.; Borman's Inc.; Commercial facilities--Michigan.; Detroit (Mich.); Farmer Jack (Grocery stores); Grocery stores--Michigan.; John Paul II, Pope, 1920-2005--Travel--Michigan--Detroit.; Parks, Rosa, 1913-2005.; Parades--Michigan--Detroit.; Shopping--Michigan.; Thanksgiving Day Parade (Detroit, Mich.)
Contributors:
Borman, Abraham.; Borman, Paul.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Borman's Inc.
  The first series is Borman's Inc. (3 linear ft.) includes files related to the business of the Borman Family corporation. Included are employee newsletters, annual reports, advertisements, correspondence, as well as photographs of people and many of the stores owned by Borman's Inc. The largest portion of this series contains site surveys, which document the company's process of selecting and monitoring potential and existing sites for supermarkets.
  - Topical Files
    - Advertisements 1966-1969 (also see oversize folder) (Box 1)
    - Annual Reports
      - 1961 (Box 1)
      - 1969-1972 (Box 1)
      - 1979-1981 (Box 1)
      - 1982-1988 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1975 (Box 1)
    - Coupon Books (Box 1)
    - Development Strategy 1972 (Box 1)
    - Employee Newsletters 1966-1969 (Box 1)
    - Financial Reports and Annual Meetings 1984-1985 (Box 1)
    - History of Borman's Inc. (Box 1)
    - Payroll 1981-1987 (Box 1)
    - Personnel and Executive Lists 1986-1987 (Box 1)
    - Photographs
      - Store exteriors, 3 folders (Box 1)
      - Store interiors (Box 1)
      - Executive Board (Box 1)
        (see also oversize folder)
      - Various People (Box 1)
    - Press Releases
      - 1959-1965 (Box 1)
      - 1967-1985 (Box 1)
    - Sales and Site Data 1964 (Box 1)
    - Speeches and Meeting Remarks 1964, 1969, 1984 (Box 1)
    - Stock Information
      - 1950-1959 (Box 2)
      - 1960-1967 (Box 2)
      - 1968 (Box 2)
  - Site Surveys
    - Michigan
      - Dearborn 1979 (Box 2)
      - Detroit 1982, 1985 (Box 2)
      - Pontiac 1987 (Box 2)
      - Sault Ste. Marie 1980 (Box 2)
      - Southfield 1969, 1979 (Box 2)
      - Southgate
        - 1969-1978 (Box 2)
        - 1980-1981 (Box 2)
      - Sterling Heights
        - 1964-1969 (Box 2)
        - 1972-1978 (Box 2)
        - 1979-1981 (Box 2)
      - Sturgis 1978 (Box 2)
      - Taylor
        - 1965-1972 (Box 2)
        - 1973-1978 (Box 2)
      - Warren
        - 1966-1974 (Box 3)
        - 1976-1980 (Box 3)
        - 1987 (Box 3)
      - Waterford 1965-1984 (Box 3)
      - Wayne 1973, 1978, 1984 (Box 3)
      - West Bloomfield
        - 1964-1968 (Box 3)
        - 1969-1982 (Box 3)
      - Westland
        - 1969-1973 (Box 3)
        - 1974-1978 (Box 3)
      - White Lake Township 1980-1981 (Box 3)
      - Woodhaven 1972, 1981 (Box 3)
      - Wyndotte 1970-1973 (Box 3)
      - Ypsilanti 1972, 1977 (Box 3)
    - Other States
      - Idaho Falls, Idaho 1987 (Box 3)
      - Pocatello, Idaho 1986-1987 (Box 3)
      - Twin Falls, Idaho 1987 (Box 3)
      - Orem, Utah 1986-1987 (Box 3)
      - Salt Lake City, Utah 1986-1987 (Box 3)
      - West Valley City, Utah 1987 (Box 3)
- Farmer Jack
  The second series, Farmer Jack (2 linear ft.), contains material relating specifically to Borman's Inc's. most well-known supermarket chain. This series includes employee newsletters, papers that relate to security issues, and financial reports, but most of the series consists of papers and photos that document Farmer Jack's public relations work.
  - Management
    - Executive Personnel Announcements 1972-1988 (Box 4)
    - Location Listings 1986, 1987 (Box 4)
    - Human Resources 1979 1979, 1980, 1989 (Box 4)
    - Meeting Minutes and Decisions 1988-1989 (Box 4)
    - Financial Progress Reports 1989 (Box 4)
    - Employee Newsletters
      - 1986-1988 (Box 4)
      - 1989-1991 (Box 4)
    - Price and Movement Book 1986 (Box 4)
    - Sale of Adrian Farmer Jack 1981 (Box 4)
    - Security 1988-1990 (Box 4)
    - Marvin Biltis Appointment 1988 (Box 4)
  - Public Relations
    - Celebrations
      - 50th Anniversary Party 1977
        - Printed Materials (Box 4)
        - Photos (Box 4)
      - Thanksgiving Day Parade 1983-1988
        - Printed Materials (Box 4)
        - Photos and Other Visual Materials (Box 4)
      - Cinco De May o Scrapbooks with Photos, 1988 (Box 4)
    - Contests
      - 50th Anniversary Prize Drawing 1977
        - Printed Materials (Box 4)
        - Photos (Box 4)
      - TV. Contest 1977 (Box 4)
      - Bake-off Contest 1977
        - Printed Materials (Box 4)
        - Photos (Box 4)
      - Israel Drawing
        - 1978 (Box 4)
        - 1979 (Box 4)
      - Easter Egg Hunt 1979
        - Printed Materials (Box 4)
        - Photos (Box 4)
      - World on Ice 1981 (Box 4)
      - Super Bowl Sweepstakes 1982
        - Printed Materials (Box 4)
        - Photos (Box 4)
      - Florida Sweepstakes 1983
        - Printed Materials (Box 5)
        - Photos (Box 5)
      - Cabbage Patch Doll Drawing 1984 (Box 5)
      - Home Cookin' Contest (contains photos)
        - 1985 (Box 5)
        - 1987 (Box 5)
    - Customer Relations
      - Customer Letters 1982, 1988 (Box 5)
      - Child ID Card Program 1985 (Box 5)
      - Want Card 1985, 1987 (Box 5)
      - Grape Boycott 1987-1988 (Box 5)
      - "The Telephone" (Box 5)
    - Newspaper Advertisements
      - 1968-1971 (Box 5)
      - 1972-1985 (Box 5)
    - Promotions
      - Iowa Meats Promo 1976 (Box 5)
      - Warehouse Sale 1977
        - Printed Materials (Box 5)
        - Photos (Box 5)
      - Double Coupons 1988 (Box 5)
      - Coupon Books (Box 5)
      - Nutriclean Program 1989 (Box 5)
      - Heartsmart Program 1989-1990 (Box 5)
      - VideoCart Program 1991 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous
      - Torch Drive 1964-1969
        - Printed Materials (Box 5)
        - Photos (Box 5)
      - The Robot 1978 (photos) (Box 5)
      - Magna Carta/Bicentennial 1986 (Box 5)
      - Chimpanzee Exhibit 1986-1987 (Box 5)
      - Greenfield Village 1987-1988 (Box 5)
      - Pope's Visit to Hamtramck, MI 1987
        - Printed Materials (Box 5)
        - Photos (Box 5)
      - Papal Memorial 1987
        - Printed Materials (Box 5)
        - Photos (Box 5)
  - Photos
    - Grand Openings
      - 1982 (Box 5)
        (include photos of Rosa Parks)
      - 1983 (Box 5)
      - 1990 (Box 5)
    - Gala Event (Box 5)
    - Farmer Jack Stores (Box 5)
    - People (Box 5)
    - Executive Board (Box 5)
- Family
  The third series, Family (1 linear ft.), includes materials relating to the Borman Family and their activities within the community. Contained within this series are genealogies, immigration documents, awards, and speeches, as well as papers related to different foundations that the Bormans were involved with.
  - Borman Family History and Genealogy, prepared in 1991, 1993 (Box 5)
  - Abraham Borman
    - Awards
      - Tribute from Yeshiva University 1960
        - Printed Materials (Box 6)
        - Photos (Box 6)
      - Israel Prime Minister's Medal 1966
        - Printed Materials (Box 6)
        - Photos (Box 6)
        - Photo Album (Box 6)
      - Tribute from Hebrew University of Jerusalem 1969 (contains photos) (Box 6)
      - Miscellaneous Awards 1961-1974 (Box 6)
    - Official Documents (Immigration papers, birth and death certificates) (Box 6)
    - Correspondence 1960-1975 (Box 6)
    - Photos (Box 6)
  - Tom Borman news articles and a photo (Box 6)
  - Paul Borman
    - Biographies 1965, 1980, 1987 (Box 6)
    - Awards
      - Man of the Year 1980 (Box 6)
      - Weizmann Banquet honoring Paul and Marlene Borman 1984 (Box 6)
      - Speeches 1974, 1981, 1986 (Box 6)
      - Letters about becoming president of Borman's Inc. 1965 (Box 6)
  - Borman Family Associations
    - Borman Foundation 1966-1984 (Box 6)
    - Weizman Institute 1983-1987 (Box 6)
    - Holocaust Memorial Center Dedication 1984 (Box 6)
  - Photos (Box 6)
    (also see oversize folder)
- News Clippings
  The News Clippings (.5 linear ft.) series contains articles from newspapers and magazines relating primarily to Borman's Inc. and Farmer Jack, but also to different members of the Borman Family. These are arranged chronologically by year. This series also includes two scrapbooks.
  - 1958-1963 (Box 6)
  - 1964-1966 (Box 6)
  - 1967-1974 (Box 6)
  - 1980-1981 (Box 6)
  - 1982-1984 (Box 7)
  - 1985-1987 (Box 7)
  - 1988-1991 (Box 7)
  - Scrapbook 1959-1964 (Box 7)
  - Scrapbook 1965-1970 (Box 7)